[Music]
hey everybody welcome back to another
prefect live i'm chris reuter and today
i'm here with ben welsh so hey ben how's
it going
good thanks for having me absolutely so
ben is an l.a times journalist and this
is really cool john s knight journalism
fellow at stanford i see you've got the
hat on today he's been spending they're
spending the year working on the big
look local news project so first thing
i'd love to hear what is the big local
news project what are you working on
sure big local news is a program at the
stanford university journalism school
that's looking to kind of become
a hub
for
gathering uh analyzing organizing uh
large data sets for use in local news
so you know
whether you know it or not there are
computer programmers in newsrooms all
across america who are using their kind
of skills to grab data wrestle it down
make sense of it and turn it into
stories to find and tell stories and the
goal of the program at stanford is to to
help newsrooms make that happen
that uh data journalism concept i think
one was definitely new to me and you you
joined the slack you started asking
questions and i really appreciate your
asking some some interesting questions
that i think will help other people get
started too so you've already been a
really helpful valuable member of the
community i really want to thank you for
that too
ben was telling me before he came on
he's originally from iowa so hard
question today
uh this is the i to me the i o question
uh cyclones or hawkeyes oh it's
definitely the iowa hawkeyes i grew up
near iowa city iowa and a big hawkeye
football fan and i go back for a game
every year i was there for penn state
last fall that's awesome
so today we're talking about the work
you've been doing has been around web
scraping i think was really probably
more relevant to a lot of the data
journalists out there but i think some
of our other community members could
definitely learn a little bit from your
use case so i know you're on gcp um do
you want to give a brief overview of
what we're going to talk about today and
then we can get right into it
yeah i was thinking i could give some
examples of the type of work that our
team does to turn data into stories into
news and then we can really dig into one
of kind of our
new projects still at an early stage
that's trying to take advantage of
prefect to really scale up what we can
pull off that sounds awesome cool so if
you're ready i'll switch over to your
screen
yeah sure can you see it yep it's all
good
great so we're starting off here right
now
with a story that our team put out just
this morning so today in the central
valley here in california lisa pick off
white who's on our big local news team
teamed up with some public radio
reporters in the area to do an
investigation into shootings by the
bakersfield police department
the local department had been under some
pressure to improve how it handles
interacting with people who have mental
health issues
though the department's official
position has continued to be in years
that that's not really a problem when it
comes to police shootings well what lisa
and her partners molly and sorith found
out did is they built a database where
one didn't exist is by filing public
records requests that are
allow us to access records thanks to a
new state law that kind of opened up
what you can get they built a database
of every police shooting by the
bakersfield police department over a
five or six year period
and then they went through and read them
all and so that's a process of like
gathering big stacks of paper and pdfs
uh that you get back from your records
request and then using a sort of
database frame of mind to kind of
convert those raw records into a
spreadsheet and into something that you
can analyze
so that you can say something a little
more authoritative than just talk about
one or two cases and if you were to
check out the story which i encourage
you to do you would see that they found
that about 40
of
uses of force during that period were
linked to or were against a person who
who you could say had some sort of
mental health or sobriety issue at the
time of the event which is much much
larger than the official police estimate
which was only about three percent so
the story unpacks all those issues and
talks about how the police department is
facing the challenge of really stepping
up to take that on and to me this is one
one example among many of the type of
work that our team tries to do
to kind of convert public records and
sort of the raw information that's out
there in the world and on the internet
into structured information that we can
interrogate analyze and report on um our
project big local news is like a website
at big local news.org
and it's also a github profile where
we're posting you know dozens of open
source code repositories that power kind
of the work that we do and in some cases
it's like lisa it's a little more uh ad
hoc where you're converting
semi-structured data into structured
data but in other cases
the process is quite a bit more
automated in our world of data
journalism a really common challenge is
what is you know i think everyone on
this call probably knows about but it's
called web scraping which is really
writing a sort of computer script or
spider that can walk across the web pull
down pages and then extract kind of
useful information out of those pages
into some kind of structured form and
you know obviously in the case of the
google spider
that's done in service of creating a
great search engine
in the case of journalists it's often uh
about getting databases out of the
government that they might not otherwise
want to get give you or it might be hard
to get at
and so
a lot of our projects on our team are
going to try to scale up large scale
scrapers that we think will be useful to
many many news organizations across the
country through the power of scale but
that the individual news organizations
really struggle to pull off on their own
and so if you check our github profile
at big local news you'll see quite a few
examples of those one that i've been
working on on recent weeks that doesn't
involve prefect but is sort of more a
finished product is related to scraping
layoff notices under something called
the warn act and so the warn act is a
federal law that requires companies to
to disclose when they lay off a lot of
people at their factory or company
but that data is not consolidated into a
single database anywhere each state
collects it separately via different
means and so with stanford graduate
students and partners in journalism
we've written web scrapers from about 40
state websites that flow those all into
a single database and then allow us to
write say a slack bot that will notify
reporters when a new listing has come in
so that's an example of like a scraper
in motion just if you're interested in
other big local news projects just
yesterday on our blog at
biglobalnews.org posts we put up this
story by dilsey mercedes mercedes which
rounds up
um about a dozen different stories from
around the world that our team worked on
partnering with news organizations to
turn data into news about covid and so
that includes
helping journalists in peru build a
database of covet among indigenous
people in the amazon who weren't being
well tracked by the government there it
also includes working with
people in the bay area in california to
analyze the billions of dollars of
emergency loans sent out by the u.s
government under the paycheck protection
program
and which found pretty wide disparities
in where those went and lots and lots of
other examples here for different news
organizations across the country and
kind of making those stories happen
through um software that we write
through records requests that we file
through partnerships with news orgs and
through like tools we put together for
reporters kind of the mission of big
local news is to make a lot of these
stories happen that wouldn't otherwise
you know be stories that are told so
that's kind of the broad overview of
what we do if anybody's interested in
learning more about it i would say check
out the website big local news dot org
or github.com
big local news
awesome i think purpose why you guys are
doing this i think but also
one of the reasons why you're talking
about it a lot of overlap with potential
use cases for some of our communities so
i think really great to see the work
that you guys are doing and also
interested i think it's just really
interesting a lot of people are doing
screen scraping believe it or not um all
throughout our community and we've seen
it screen scraping and pdf scraping we
just had a blog that came out actually
on a pdf called pdf to snowflake by john
luciano on our team which did something
very very similar
that's awesome i mean parsing pdfs is
really a big challenge for us in the
police accountability work you know you
file a records request
and you often get back hundreds or
thousands of pages of pdfs that are in
really unusual shapes and sizes you also
we're also getting a lot of unstructured
video as well from those requests like
uh
body cam footage and so one of our major
projects over the next year i won't get
too in-depth about here today but we're
definitely looking for tech people to
help on
is how can we
build kind of a big database of pdfs and
video
and get some entity extraction going on
so that we can search and find stories
in that haystack of information
without it costing a ton of money right
and in a way that ultimately yields kind
of stories
um so where's prefect come in though
right should we get to get to that yeah
let's do it okay cool so like one of the
big projects i worked on the last couple
years was obviously covering the
coronavirus
at the los angeles times i was until
recently the editor of the data and
graphics department and one of our major
initiatives was to track coronavirus in
the state of california he was starting
um in march 2020 we began writing web
scrapers for all kinds of uh state
websites but also for the 58 counties
across the state to try to get as much
information about covet as possible and
we ultimately were able to create a web
scraping system that runs open source on
github at california coronavirus
scrapers that runs something like 50 to
100 web scrapers you know all throughout
the day and night to pull down data that
then goes on to um
the
you know the the data portal that is
kind of the most popular page on the
last website where the numbers are then
surfaced for the general public and in
this case we were able to get by just
using kind of github actions and little
itty bitty python scripts because none
of them were especially that complicated
and the data that we were gathering was
pretty
um you know by silicon valley standards
pretty small or simple right a few
hundred or a few thousand records a
single file and it really was just
writing about a lot of little scrapers
doing that we were able to pull it off
entirely for free using this kind of
system but that's not you know there's
often challenges that are bigger than
that where we need bigger and better
tools which is where prefix comes in and
you know part of the goal of big local
news is to do scrapers that are bigger
than news organizations can really pull
off on their own right and there's a
couple classic examples of this
that news organizations across the
country have all kind of tried and
mostly failed to come up with a
sustainable solution
and that's really to monitor your local
government and analyze it better through
gathering data one would be you know
your city council everyone has a county
government or a city government that has
some kind
of website that is just churning through
documents about agendas meetings votes
decisions happening in local government
and the other is your county courthouse
which is where local judges are making
decisions about who goes to jail who
doesn't juries as well
and a lot of power is being exercised
and in pretty much every newsroom in the
united states of a certain size at one
time or another your local uh newsroom
has had a nerd who's tried to write the
scraper for that system
and and many and it's some fraction of
those cases they've actually succeeded
hooray right and maybe you came up with
like a little private search that ran
under their desk at the office right or
maybe you did like a couple good
investigative stories where you analyzed
evictions by landlords or
racial disparities and sentencing or who
knows what
um but you know ultimately that nerd got
another job
or
the county website changed and just like
keeping those kinds of systems up and
sustainable there just really hasn't
been a solution for that and so that's
that's a like space to use the tech word
where big local news is looking to kind
of enter and see if we can we can come
up with something that's a little
sturdier and so we have two open source
repositories
you can find on the big local news site
one is called civic scraper and the
other is called uh court scraper let me
call that up real quick and they're you
know just free and open python
libraries like you've seen before that
have kind of class-based systems
for
um scraping kind of the major
platforms or vendors that serve hundreds
of local governments across the country
so there's really five or six companies
that create kind of products they sell
to local governments to do court records
or to do city council records and if you
can write a scraper
that extracts the data
from those vendors sites you get a lot
of bang for your buck you know there's
one vendor called civic plus
uh who you can find inside this
repository and if you scrape all the
civic plus websites or all the granicus
websites that's another one you're
you're suddenly gathering
city council records or capable of
gathering city council records from
literally hundreds of governments across
the country and so our goal is to to try
to get as much bang for the buck as
possible to write scrapers that really
target the large vendors that serve lots
of areas and then to run
spiders that then
jump across as many local venues as
possible and try to build one big
national database of
city council agendas and county court
decisions
and so
we're at a stage of these projects where
we've got kind of the draft python
applications we've got some of these
scrapers ready to go but now we actually
need to run the damn things right and
github actions is great but if you're
going to scrape
500 county court websites or whatever it
ends up being and each one of those
scrapers is going to take a really
extended amount of time
and if they're going to need to store
data a lot of data in a pretty big data
pool somewhere you know then that kind
of free tool you're using on github
actions doesn't look so great anymore
right and you really need to find a way
to scale up and i'll be honest with you
within the sort of like hacker world of
journalism where there isn't a lot of
money to be made
and we're all kind of like people like
me people who went to journalism school
and are like faker coders
you know there really hasn't this
problem like really hasn't been solved
within our little like niche and so
this is part of where we're getting
stanford behind it we're trying out a
tool like prefect our goal is to kind of
go a little further than you than the
news organizations have really gone
before i suspect some of these problems
might seem small to people who work at
big tech but they're
you know we're trying to get over a
pretty big hump for journalism to try to
step it up to another level and so
what i've been working on the last
couple months isn't really these
scrapers it's the prefect integration
and so
um you can see here here's here this is
the private repository now and so this
is a private repository called the civic
prefect flow
and this is my kind of current effort to
take that open source civic scraper code
we were just looking at from pi pi and
the open source world of python and
install it so that it's ready to be
plugged into a kubernetes cluster
running in google cloud
a sort of whole prefect kit so that
we'll be able to schedule tasks that
will run across hundreds or maybe even
thousands of sites before we're done and
so
this is um
this is you know pretty basic prefix
stuff but you can see that it's based on
a github template which is also open
source so we've created an open source
template called prefect flow template
which is kind of my the current like
best knowledge that i've been able to
assemble for myself personally by
bugging chris and his colleagues at
slack by doing a lot of hacking
uh on my own time at work is this is
kind of the bare bones for how you would
take a prefect flow and plug it into
kubernetes and um
and google google cloud and so you can
see it here some pretty basic like hacks
i've come up with for managing
development versus production
environments
where the code itself is going to be
stuffed up into docker inside the google
artifact registry
and
the uh run is going to be done by a
kubernetes agent the size of which is
kind of dictated by some of this config
here
and this code
is pretty much ready to go for anyone
who would want to experiment with it or
try to use it
besides just kind of figuring out how to
manage the toggle between the two
environments i'm pretty proud of what
we've been able to do here with uh
github actions integration where we have
a workflow that's included with this
that has kind of a continuous deployment
so that every time you you've ever done
a github release every time you do a
release on github or you kick out a new
version this will actually trigger a
deployment into google cloud
um automatically
where um
the docker in image with the code that's
going to be run will be re-uploaded and
versioned
into google artifact registry and the
prefect flow will be re-registered with
our prefect account kind of
automatically and so just through a
little bit of kind of configuration of
some of these goofy tools you can make
it so that you're able to push out
new iterations of
the kind of flow um without it being a
big
goddamn hassle to like
shove shove the vcr tape into the google
um you know vcr
and so that all kind of ends up inside a
kubernetes cluster which you can see
here where right now the only thing
running is currently our prefect agent
which is sort of you know the all was on
watcher that's waiting to be told to do
something
and uh that's configured through a
separate private repository by the way
which if people are interested in how to
do a prefect agent which is a little
different from doing a prefect flow and
it's kind of part of learning how to how
to uh learning how to dougie within this
kind of system we've got a private um
repo there i'd be happy to share some of
the stuff i've learned on and we
actually did a post on our blog
which walks through all the steps on how
to deploy your prefect agent to google
kubernetes engine
um which is just a lot of really
annoying g cloud commands um which i'd
be happy to talk about but i don't want
to bore you but the result is is that
when the prefix scheduled task is
kickstarted within prefect it's able the
agent will pick it up and then we'll
just create workers here
as dictated in the flow
uh and they'll do the thing and keep
moving and so
we're at a stage now where we've kind of
like learned enough prefect to get all
the kind of ducks in a row and the
pieces in place and over the next few
weeks we're going to look to really
start slotting in the scraper and
scaling up how much data we're gathering
that's something that's that's still
actually ahead of us but my hope is is
that by the end of this month we'll
really be skate we'll be running one of
the biggest scrapers in journalism i
think by the end of the month which is
pretty exciting then we got to figure
out what we're going to do with all that
data which is a whole other challenge of
analysis and
data science but that's a separate kind
of question entirely i suppose that's
awesome it's really funny i think two
weeks in a row we've had community
members on predict live in two weeks in
a row it's been the same pattern of
deploying a docker agent via github
actions um or so it's it's it's
interesting to see you're doing it in
google cloud i think that henning who
was on last week was doing a picture but
it's an interesting pattern that that
we're seeing out there and i think will
be really really helpful um if other
people were to see it so i will
highlight this blog post when we when we
post it on youtube too
the trick is really getting into this
thing called the google artifact
registry which is really like their
private version of pi pi in some ways
right it's a place where you can like
ship private python packages private
docker images
and then um version them so they can
kind of get kicked out so here's the
docker image for our agent and here's
the docker image for that prefect flow
and every time we do a github release it
just stuffs another version of it kind
of in here right
um so you can see this one's been
versioned a few times and
um and so like learning that is kind of
the trick uh on the google cloud side
and then the github action side we have
another post that kind of shows this too
which is um
how to push tagged release to google
artifact registry with github action
this really gets at the challenge of
integration with github which is not
especially hard but it requires you to
create you create this thing called a
service worker or a workload identity
federation which is really just a bunch
of gobbledygook for like how do you
create a special user that github is
allowed to use to muck around with your
google cloud right
but like just like creating the user for
the action to talk to google cloud
requires like six or seven like crazy g
cloud commands and like permissions and
so the first time you do it it's kind of
wild and crazy but once you once you're
done with it it's pretty simple to just
like plug it in
you you have a talent for synthesizing
things in a really i think
interesting way and i i would agree with
you it is just a bunch of gobbledygook
in order to to create a essential oh my
god a workload identity pool versus like
a workload identity provider like you
know come on yeah
um so we you and i were talking before
we went live a little bit about your
experience we started started with
prefect 2 and i think that a lot of a
lot of users
experienced maybe some of the same
challenges you may have if you i'd love
for you to talk about those a little bit
briefly and then maybe we can help to
push you yeah in the right direction and
then secondly if you have any any
thoughts or experience on prefect 2
which is or orion yeah i mean so i'm a
python guy i've been doing python for 15
years or whatever i wouldn't say i'm an
expert i'm more of like a journalist
hacker type but i'm comfortable with
python it's what i like
i have opinions about it you know what i
mean i've gotten to that stage but like
um and so prefect i think is a really
great thing for a python person to get
started because it's really
well put together python code i think
anyone who's a veteran at it will kind
of recognize that pretty quickly they
have a lot of really good examples of
how they made flows happen to me the
real challenge wasn't the prefect code
or the python which i thought came
pretty quick to me the challenge was
figuring out how to integrate it with
google cloud and my hosting provider
right where it's like okay so i've got
this flow
like how do i get it up somewhere so
it's like running and like what exactly
is an agent as opposed to my flow and
how do i make all those kind of things
like run within the provider
was really the challenge and the way i
got there was just like through you know
embarrassing questions and kind of
stumbling my way in the prefect slack so
i really wouldn't i mean it worked great
for me i would really say anyone who's
getting started get into the prefect
slack and just like just ask the
questions like how do i do this
and you know you might be that you know
it could be that you're the first person
to ask this or that but you probably
aren't and the folks in there can kind
of point you to some other resources
that's a big reason i wrote these blog
posts as well myself and put together
the open source flow template is one i
want our team and other people on my
team to be able to learn this because
i'm like our kind of explorer on this
but i also just want to make it so other
folks can pick up the tech without it
being a big hassle too absolutely
have you you thought have you read about
2.0 at all or have you thought about i
know it's like a thing and it's it's
it's pitched to be better but i to be
honest with you i haven't even looked at
it yep yet no worries um and then
scaling is one thing i wanted to touch
on too that we did talk about earlier a
little bit i know you probably really
have no like no idea what like what the
core usage will be right but um how much
how much data are you looking to scrape
broadly if you can say that maybe number
of pages yeah i mean we haven't really
done the estimate which we should
you know um but i think it's gonna be
millions of artifacts you know what i
mean it's gonna be
because if you think about it like
you know if you go through the major
courthouses in the state of california
you know the five or ten biggest
counties are doing tens of thousands of
cases every year you know in their local
county courthouses and then every one of
those cases may have multiple records
depending on how the website's set up
and so i think that stuff's going to
multiply pretty quickly so i think we'll
probably end up in the millions or tens
of millions of records
without much trouble without before we
get too far
you know um so i think it's it's going
to be in that ballpark which for
journalism is big you know
yeah and we i mean we're really
interested to follow the
failing story and i think it'll be
really really cool to i mean you have to
have you back on here at least to see uh
how fast how much you've scaled and how
totally yeah and i think because there's
going to be two things to it there's the
workers to just go get it but then
there's just like the static files which
is like where do we stick them and then
how do we do anything with them
efficiently this is one thing that you
know you know some of my good friends
work on
the panama papers or the pandora papers
which are projects i bet people on
you've heard about which are these huge
leaks from central american law firms
um
that you know that hold offshore
accounts for the world's wealthy and
they have to deal with you know millions
of pdfs and records for their stories
and they find
that um it's so costly to run like a
data science operation across the entire
set that they tend not just to do it you
know there's a way in which i think
there's a lot of potential
to take what people have you know
developed in machine learning and and ai
techniques to
to try to to bring more out of these
like data sets that have a high public
interest value but the cost is is really
sometimes an issue and then you know
even though we are hackers and coders
you know we're not ai specialists right
you know and so
knowing the right thing to do is often
kind of a trick absolutely so if if
people want to know how to support you
or big local news how can they do so
well i mean we got all this code that's
open source you know the warren project
i just talked about briefly has more
than a dozen outside contributors and so
if you're interested in writing a web
scraper that's part of one of our
projects or just getting involved and
improving some of our open source code
there's a lot of opportunities on the
github page just to jump in and grab a
ticket and do it um also like you can
always just reach out to me and i'd be
happy to plug in this way or that way um
in terms of some of our more the bigger
projects that i was talking about if
people want to are interested more in
the big think of it or how we go about
the bigger issues just go ahead and
reach out you know i know that there's a
lot of interest in the tech world and
police accountability and some of these
other stories and you know your talent
and your knowledge is something that we
could probably learn from so would be
happy to really talk with anybody
awesome
then unless you have anything else you
want to share i really really appreciate
you coming on uh prefix live and
anything else for for the crew out there
no i mean thanks for having me um thanks
for creating kind of a positive
community thanks for putting up with my
coughing i had i had a non-covered flu
last week which i think i'm mostly over
but i'm not quite there yet absolutely
well thanks for being a part of the
community and i think you
along with everyone else but you have
helped to contribute to that positive
community so that's that's you for sure
too so thanks everyone for watching um
and we'll see you soon see you ben
thank you